<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before His Majesty at Whitehall, March 12, 1664/5 by B. Lord Bishop of Lincoln.</title>
            <author>Laney, Benjamin, 1591-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17030</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11859605</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11859605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 499:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before His Majesty at Whitehall, March 12, 1664/5 by B. Lord Bishop of Lincoln.</title>
                  <author>Laney, Benjamin, 1591-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Timothy Garthwait,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 1st, IV, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Quietude --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50002:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before HIS MAJESTY at <hi>Whitehall, March</hi> 12. 1664/5.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>B.</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Timothy Garthwait,</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:50002:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50002:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 THESS. 4.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And that ye ſtudy to be quiet.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND</hi>] is a word that takes hold of ſomething that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without which the ſenſe of that which follows is not full. That which went next before is, <hi>We beſeech you to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe more and more. We beſeech you,</hi> is that we are to take into the Text, and then it runs thus, <hi>We beſeech you to ſtudy to be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all the uſe I ſhall make of it, now we have it here, is but to give you a taſte before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of the nature and quality of this duty, That it is no trivial thing little to be regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that which obliged S. <hi>Paul, Sylvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus,</hi> for they all joyn'd in it, to be ſo earneſt, as to beſeech them to ſtudy to be quiet. 2. And that which commends this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the more is, (as we uſe to ſay, Men are beſt known by the company they keep) <hi>And</hi>] brings in this Duty in the company of the beſt of Vertues, Charity, for that place S. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50002:3"/>gives it above all;<note place="margin">Col. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Above all things put on Charity, which is the bond of perfection.</hi> To ſtudy to be quiet, and to increaſe in brotherly love and charity, for that led the way before, are two duties bound together in the ſame Exhortation. 3. Quiet is not onely a fit companion for Charity, but an Allie to it, and grows out of it, as the branch out of the ſtock; for where brotherly love is, there will be alwayes quiet too. 4. To make all ſuit the better with Charity, the Exhortation is advanced by a Dialect of Love, <hi>We bèſeech you. Paul, Sylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus,</hi> were all Apoſtolical men, and might command, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelf in another caſe to <hi>Philemon, Though I might be bold to enjoyn thee, yet for loves ſake I rather beſeech you.</hi> And laſtly, that which might very well ſet this edge upon their affections, was, that which happened to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> at their firſt converſion; for this Epiſtle was written im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after. The ſtory we have in the 17 <hi>chap.</hi> of the <hi>Acts:</hi> When S. <hi>Paul</hi> had preach'd the Goſpel to them, and with good ſucceſs; for <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Some of them believed, and conſorted with</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Silas, <hi>and of the devout Greeks a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few.</hi> But <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>The Jews who believed not, moved with envy,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50002:3"/>took unto them certain lewd fellows of the baſer ſort, and gathered a company, and ſet all the City in an uproar, and aſſaulted the houſe of</hi> Jaſon, <hi>and ſought to bring them out to the people;</hi> mad enough of themſelves; but the more to ferment and enrage them, they charge the Apoſtles with the fault that they themſelves were acting; <hi>Theſe are they that turn the world upſide-down.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> having eſcaped this fury by going to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> and there conſidering in what a caſe he left his new Converts, both them and their Doctrine; them in a furious tumult, and their Doctrine under the reproach of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the world; out of a zeal, no doubt, and deſire to remove that ſcandal from the Faith, of all things begs and beſeecheth them to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how will this concern us? I wiſh we never had, and had not ſtill the ſame occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is not ſo long ſince, that we ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get how our late troubles firſt brake in upon our quiet: VVe had unbelieving Jews then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us too, and ſome, as was thought, in the literal ſence; who moved with envy of the times, took unto them likewiſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of lewd fellows of the baſer ſort, ſet the City in an uproar; and we may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50002:4"/>whoſe houſes they beſet (as the Jews did <hi>Jaſons</hi>) none of the meaneſt, and cried out for that juſtice which themſelves deſerved. And there were Religions in the world then too many, to the ſcandal of the true, who led on, and blew up thoſe tumults: And even now, though (God be thanked) they dare not be ſo bold to aſſault us in the ſtreets, and beſet our houſes as they did then; yet ſtill keep their quarters and leaguers within doors, with more ſecreſie, but no leſs danger.</p>
            <p>It will not therefore be unſeaſonable for us now, who have the ſame cauſe the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had, with the ſame affection the Apoſtle did, to beſeech you to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet.</hi> VVe have all need of quiet, and quiet it ſeems hath need of ſtudy, and ſtudy hath need of Gods bleſſing, and therefore before we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further, Let us pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THe parts of the Text are two; VVhat we are to ſtudy, And that we are to ſtudy. Firſt, VVhat? <hi>That ye ſtudy to be quiet.</hi> Quiet is here commended under the notion and quality of an Art or Science; for we are injoyned to ſtudy it. And in them we are to look, firſt, to the object, the nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50002:4"/>of it; and then to the Principles and Theorems whereon the Art is grounded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the nature and kind of this Quiet firſt: For there be many things lay claim to this word, which are either unfit for our ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or improper to this place. As firſt, there is a quiet from all motion or action that is good or uſeful; to do nothing but eat and drink and ſleep, or worſe: Away with that quiet; it neither deſerves our ſtudy, nor needs it. This is <hi>Negotioſa quies;</hi> we are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the words following to be buſie as well as quiet; we are both to ſtudy to be quiet, and to do our own buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a Quiet, not ſimply from all, but publick buſineſs; when men retire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for private ſtudy or devotion. This may be allowed, and commended too, when the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of their Countreys requires them not. But becauſe publick imployments are ſeldome forced upon any, nor need to be; for no mans parts or abilities are ſo great, which may not truly, and certainly will be thought ſuch as can very well be ſpared: They therefore who affect that privacy, may be ſecure from that neceſſity; they who have a will to be quiet for devotion or ſtudy, need not ſtudy to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50002:5"/>quiet, the acceſs to that is eaſie enough.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is another Quiet, more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in its ſelf, and needs our ſtudy too; To compoſe our unruly and diſordered paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and affections, which raiſe tumults and commotions within us, that will not ſuffer us to be at reſt or quiet day or night. In the midſt therefore of all the temptations of good, or ſtorms of ill fortune to reſt ſecurely and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly, whatſoever happens to our private, is certainly an admirable temper, and well worthy our beſt care and ſtudy; and was that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf it ſeems ſtudied, for he ſaid he learned it; <hi>I have learned in what eſtate ſoever I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>therewith to be content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the quiet we are here to ſtudy is not properly within us, but without us; it is not ſimply a quiet from motion, but com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>motion, a troubling of others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And that I may contract my argument and bring it into as narrow a compaſs as may be, I ſhall not take in every of the diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of the quiet of others: No not that which is the greateſt of all, and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to peace and quiet, Civil Wars and broils. The miſchiefs of that we have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo lately to our coſt, and ſo perfectly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50002:5"/>that I hope we need not be ſet to ſtudy that now: when every good man was put to his ſtudy how to live, and when vile and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible wretches ranted in plenty and power.</p>
            <p>The horrid fruits and conſequences of that great diſturber of quiet, <hi>War,</hi> have induc'd ſome learned men, as well as others, to think all wars unlawful; I ſhould have been much inclined to that opinion upon the ſtricteſt rules of Chriſtianity, if War were not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times neceſſary to Peace. A forraign War for that reaſon may be lawful, but a civil and domeſtick never. And the reaſon of this difference is, becauſe for the compoſing of all quarrels that may ariſe between ſubjects, God hath by his Ordinance provided a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in Princes and Magiſtrates, from whom alone we are to ſeek for revenge or defence. But for ſuch differences as ariſe between free Princes and States, becauſe there is no Judg on earth, to whom they may have recourſe for their relief, being deſtitute of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon remedy, they may, without queſtion, make uſe of that ſword which God hath put into their hands to defend their ſubjects from the injuries as well of ſtrangers as their own.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50002:6"/>Nor are they in this Judges in their own cauſe, which hath ſome appearance of injuſtice; for a forraign War, for defect of a competent Judg on Earth, is but an appeal to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Judg of Heaven and Earth. And when they go into the Field, it is but to plead their cauſe before God, with whom are the iſſues of VVar. Onely they had need be careful, that the cauſe they bring before him be good; For ſhall not the Judg of all the world do right? But the muſt leave this to Princes and their Miniſters, who are the onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtudents of that quiet, which is diſturbed by VVar, and come to that which may and muſt be the ſtudy of us all: That is, <hi>a quiet from troubles that ariſe from different judgments and perſwaſions in matters of Religion,</hi> which cauſe ſects and diviſions in it, though they break not out into an open VVar. Not that VVar be quite left out of the ſectaries recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. For though Civil VVars and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have their beginning for the moſt part from the ambition or diſcontent of a few, yet becauſe the people, who are the neceſſary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of that miſchief, be not apt to ſerve the ambition of others, if it comes bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced to them, the mask of Religion is always
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50002:6"/>put on, wherein all people are concerned, which makes it a common and popular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. And therefore you ſhall ſcarce hear of a Rebellion of late times, in which Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion did not carry the Colours at leaſt, if not command in chief.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall nevertheleſs at this time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to make that any part of the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks charge, but treat them upon their own terms, that they are as great enemies to War as any that object it to them: Yet I muſt charge them all to be guilty of the breach of peace and quiet in the Church, and that not accidentally, which may ſometimes bear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, but neceſſarily; it is connatural and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the very nature of ſchiſm, which is a rent or diviſion, ſo the word ſignifies. It is the worſt diſturbance that can be to any body, to be torn in pieces. It diſſolves the bonds by which the parts are joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpecially that which unites them to the Head; for ſchiſme in the Churches no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is properly a ſeparation from the Head and authority, and is the ſame in the Church that Rebellion or Treaſon is in the State. Now as every diſobedience to the King and the Laws is not Treaſon, though againſt the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50002:7"/>King, but the diſclaiming the right and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the King hath to govern, and the practice of ſuch things, by which his <hi>Regalia</hi> and rights are uſurpt by others, as to make War, to make Laws, to thruſt Officers upon him, to order the Coin, theſe and of the like kind are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Treaſon. So every error or diſobedience in Religion makes not a ſchiſme, but the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the right and power the Church hath to govern them, and a uſurpation of a right to themſelves, to order and frame points of Belief, and Forms how to ſerve and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, apart from the Church, for ſo went the ſtyle of the ancient Church for Schiſme, <hi>altare contra altare,</hi> which in our modern dialect is a Conventicle againſt the Church. For though Schiſm be formally a ſeparation from the Head, yet conſequently it works upon the members; for that which was at firſt but difference of opinion, ſoon begets a diſaffection, and from that grows to hatred and contempt, and ſo falls into the practice of ſuch things as deſtroy the very being and power of Religion, which conſiſts in the mutual offices of Charity; and though this miſchief breaks not out into an actual War, yet is always accompanied with moſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50002:7"/>unnatural and unchriſtian practiſes, as S. <hi>James</hi> long ſince obſerved, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Where envy and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evil work.</hi> Now to avoid all this, it will highly concern us to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having cleared the firſt Point, the Object of our ſtudy, <hi>Quiet,</hi> and wherein the <hi>ſormalis ratio</hi> of it conſiſts, and how it comes to be diſturbed by Schiſm: The next Point is, to enquire into the Principles whereon we are to ground our ſtudy; for if there ſhould be an errour or miſtake in them, all our labour and ſtudy is loſt, or worſe; for an inveterate, grounded, ſtudied errour is ſo much the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be reclaimed. It was no unreaſonable demand therefore of the Philoſopher, who asked a double reward for thoſe Scholars that had been already entred into the ſtudy of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, becauſe his pains would be double with them, to undoe firſt, and caſt out thoſe falſe prejudices which they had already lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Now if it ſhould happen, that they which are otherwiſe ſtudious and deſirous of peace, ſhould not do the things that make for peace, as the Apoſtle requires,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.10.</note> our ſtudy will grow upon us, firſt to unlearn thoſe falſe deceitfull
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50002:8"/>principles of peace, before we enquire into the true: Of ſome of the chief of theſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall give you an account in the firſt place. It will conduce much to the peace of the Church, they ſay, Firſt,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>If Religion were free, and all compulſory means forborne,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>If meer Errours in Judgment howſoever were not puniſhed as crimes, which is not in the power of any to help.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Or if that, yet</hi> (Thirdly) <hi>That omiſsion of Forms and Ceremonies were not more ſeverely and frequently puniſhed, then notoriouus and ſcandalous crimes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>If fewer Articles and Points of Religion were defined, it would make more room in the Church for thoſe that diſſent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. Another is, <hi>If men of moderate Opinions were onely imployed in the Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. The laſt, and moſt importunate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to peace, is, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>But that none of all theſe are things that make for peace, I ſhall ſhew with as much brevity as the matter is capable of; as firſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not the forbearance of all compulſory means by puniſhments, which, they ſay, is repugnant to that freeneſs with which Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50002:8"/>ſhould be entertained, and onely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces men to an hypocritical obedience to that which in their judgements they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</p>
            <p>Religion, I grant, ſhould be free; it is no Religion which is not ſo: But it is as true, that every other act of vertue, and obedience to the Laws ſhould be free likewiſe; but therefore not to puniſh them that tranſgreſs, were to proclaim a perpetual Jubile, and ſet open all priſon doors: God would never have enjoyned the Magiſtrate to puniſh tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, nor himſelf threatned to puniſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, if the fear of that did corrupt our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: For our Saviour in the Parable, when the gueſts came not to the banquet at his invitation,<note place="margin">Luk. 14.23.</note> commanded his ſervants to compel them to come in. And where they ſay, the fruit of that is but hypocriſie; Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites they are like enough to be, but from a worſe cauſe, not from the puniſhment, but their own frailties, becauſe they prefer their temporal ſafety before the eternal bleſſing which Chriſt hath promiſed to all that ſuffer for his ſake and the truth. Secondly, It is true, that puniſhments reach not directly the inward man, nor do they teach or inform the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50002:9"/>Judgment, that is, they do not perfect the work; but are nevertheleſs a good beginning to it: For, <hi>Fear is the beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> which <hi>Love</hi> muſt <hi>perfect.</hi> Though the Needle ſtayes not in the Garment, yet it muſt lead the Thred that makes it up. The Rod indeed doth not teach the child, yet ſcares him to his book where he may learn: So though puniſhments do not perfect and accompliſh our duty, yet they ſet us to our ſtudies, to conſider that we do not raſhly caſt our ſelves upon danger, which otherwiſe poſſibly we would never think off, but run on whither our wild vain fancies and groundleſs perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions led us: For <hi>Spes impunitatis eſt illecebra pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi.</hi> Puniſhments therefore are both juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for the good they do, and are abſolved from the evil they are pretended to do; and therefore wholly to forbear them in matters of Religion is no good principle whereon to ground the Churches peace</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The next is, <hi>That howſoever it be in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, it would make much for the quiet of the Church, if Errours in Judgment were not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as crimes, becauſe no man can be abler and wiſer then God hath made him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, that an Errour, ſo long as it ſtays
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50002:9"/>in the Underſtanding, and goes no further, is not properly a ſin; for the Underſtanding is not <hi>agens liberum,</hi> but paſsive. In that the eye of the mind is as the eye of the body; if that be naturally ſhort-ſighted, it is no fault that it ſees not ſo far as another: But if the weakneſs of the Underſtanding participate with the Will, which is <hi>agens liberum,</hi> and ſo the Errour comes within our power, then it may be properly a ſin. This is the caſe of all that diſſent in Sects; for though in ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Underſtanding is diſtinct from the Will, yet in practiſe they are ſeldome ſevered. For it is morally impoſsible, that after a man hath conceived an opinion, he ſhould not be well pleaſed with it, and have a will as occaſion is to defend and propagate it too. And when it is <hi>Voluntarium,</hi> no doubt but it is <hi>Peccatum,</hi> and when error grows to be a ſin, I know no reaſon why it may not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; for <hi>intereſt reipublicae peccata puniri.</hi> But for all that it is, they ſay, a great diſturbance of quiet to be tied to aſſent to that we cannot know nor comprehend. That's a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. I know there is much exception taken to the too punctual definitions of ſome myſteries of the faith, and particularly in the Creed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50002:10"/>commonly called by <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> where there are many particulars which they cannot know nor comprehend. Whereas in truth it is not required of them, they are not bound to know them, but to believe them; for it is the mercy of God, that the defect of our knowledg may be ſupplyed by the knowledg of others; for to believe is to ſee with other mens eyes, as knowledg is with our own.</p>
            <p>But may we ſafely truſt others in that which ſo neerly concerns as a Creed? Yes ſure, and it is as well the mercy, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, that we ſhould truſt thoſe that watch over our ſouls; yet ſtill that muſt be to ſupply the defect of our knowledg, not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; for the Church is not Lord of our Faith, but helper of our Ignorance. It ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the defect of our ſight, it doth not put it out: for if a man knows the contrary, he is not bound to believe others; for if he can ſee with his own eyes, why ſhall he be tied to ſee with other mens?</p>
            <p>But then we muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt not knowing the negative, and a poſitive know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the contrary: for if we refuſe to believe meerly becauſe we do not know or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, we leave no place for Faith at all, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50002:10"/>is the benefit to ſee by others. And for that poſitive knowledg which diſcharges us of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving others, that we be not miſtaken, it is not every conjectural or probable perſwaſion will do it, but certain knowledg: and when that is, we may ſafely learn from the Schools; <hi>Ubi non eſt formido contrarii,</hi> after diligent ſearch and enquiry, when there remains no ſcruple, doubt, or fear of the contrary, when the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is fixed, we are ſaid to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p>If this knowledge will ſerve to diſcharge us of believing others, every one that diſſents will ſay he knows the contrary, yea, and if need be will ſwear to it too; for that's an expedient lately found out to obtain that liberty, That they may be admitted to ſwear they know the contrary to that which is commanded. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if they will ſay it, and think ſo too, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſwear it or no, I think we may ſafely abſolve them from the guilt of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obdience: but that muſt be <hi>in foro Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae</hi> onely, and let them make the beſt uſe they can of that; yet <hi>in foro externo</hi> we can not; for there the Judge muſt give ſentence according to <hi>his</hi> knowledge, and not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the knowledg of the party, if he will do
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50002:11"/>juſtice. And that courſe can be no good friend to Peace, which is an enemy to Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Though Errours may be puniſhed, yet it troubles the quiet of many, that <hi>the omiſſion of Forms and Ceremonies is more ſeverely puniſhed then ſome foul and ſcandalous crimes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, Firſt, That they who object this, are not to be truſted with the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of ſins, for we know how the Market went for them when they held the Scale: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the King and the Laws, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God according to them, were the great ſcandalous crimes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Allowing it to be true as they ſay, That omiſſion of Forms and Ceremonies is by the Church more frequently and ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then greater faults. But how greater? It may be in their proper and natural guilt and obliquity, according to which ſentence ſhall be given at the day of Judgment, and to death eternal. But our earthly Tribunals are not erected to anticipate the day of Judgment, to bring all ſinners to trial for whatſoever they have committed in the fleſh; and according to the proper meaſure of their guilt; but for a particular end and uſe; that people, while they live here in the world, and in ſociety,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50002:11"/>may be kept in good order and quiet, from doing or receiving injuries. And to this end is the degree of their puniſhments commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurate: Treaſon and Rebellion are more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed in the State then many other hainous crimes, becauſe they deſtroy the very foundation of government and Society. And for the ſame reaſon, a ſchiſmatical diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though but in matters of Form and Ceremony, is purſued with more care and ſtrictneſs, becauſe it deſtroys the very end for which the power is given the Church to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, which is, the preſervation of peace and unity.</p>
            <p>For though the Paſtors of the Church may and muſt by way of <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> the better to prepare us for our account at the great and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Judgment, give every ſin the proper weight and meaſure of guilt, that is by way of Inſtruction: But by way of <hi>Correction</hi> the Church is bound up to certain cauſes, and if they keep not their bounds, they ſhall be ſure to hear of a <hi>prohibition;</hi> and thoſe Cauſes are eſpecially ſuch, for which the power is onely given, That the peaceable orderly Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God be not diſturbed.</p>
            <p>For though they are ever telling us, it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50002:12"/>for trifles, ceremonies, or indifferent things, it is but the ſame quarrel the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> have againſt God himſelf, for being ſo much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended for an Apple, a trifle which ſcarce any man that hath an Orchard would have been troubled with; and one Anſwer will ſerve both in effect. In that forbidden fruit, Gods authority in commanding, and <hi>Adams</hi> duty in obeying, were ſymbolically engaged for him and his, and there was venome enough in that to infect both. The Rites and Ceremonies of the Church, in like manner, though not in like degree, though in their opinion as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable as the <hi>paring</hi> of <hi>Adams</hi> apple, yet when diſcord and diſobedience is found with them, there is poyſon enough in that for the ſtrongeſt antidote the Church doth at any time make uſe of. Let not that therefore miſ-lead or diſturb our Student of Quiet.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Nor that which, in the Fourth place, they look at as another Expedient for Peace, <hi>If fewer Points and Articles of Religion were defined,</hi> that ſo the Church-door may be wider open to let in thoſe whoſe diſſent now troubles the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>It is fit, I grant, the Church-door ſhould ſtand always open, but for ſuch as ſhall be fit
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50002:12"/>to enter; for it would be a dangerous thing to ſet any door ſo wide open to let in an enemy upon us. But to what purpoſe would we have the Church-door ſo wide, when the Gate of Heaven is ſtrait? why ſhould they be taken in here, if they ſhall be turned back there? The Church is a City, as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a City that is at unity in it ſelf; ſo it is a City too that hath gates and walls to ſhut our others.</p>
            <p>He that came to a little City, where there was a great Gate, merrily warned the Citizens to take heed leſt their City went not out at the Gate, may ſoberly be ſaid to thoſe that would have the Church door ſo wide to let in all Sects, to take heed leſt the Church gets not out at the door: For where ſo many Religions are, it may be feared, that ſoon there will be none at all. If we be not, as the Apoſtle commands, built up in the ſame Faith, it will avail us little to be found within the ſame walls.</p>
            <p>It is therefore a perverſe remedy for peace, to abate or diminiſh the Articles and definitions of the Church, which were made of purpoſe to take away controverſies; it would be a ſtrange courſe to end controverſies, to take away the definitions. Our Student muſt read his Books back ward, if he ſeek for peace from hence. We
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50002:13"/>might as well ſay, all the world would be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, if there were no Judges nor Laws to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine differences.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> There is another Expedient for Peace, which I hear much ſpoken of, and highly ſet by as a great point of prudence, <hi>If men of moderate opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were onely taken into imployment in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moderation, I confeſs, is an excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and much to be deſired; <hi>Let your modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be known unto all men,</hi> Phil. 4 5. But then it muſt be in a ſubject capable of it, wherein there are extremes and exceſſes to be mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derated, as there is certainly in our paſſions, there it is proper. S. <hi>Paul</hi> gives it for a Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to all Students in Religion, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking, be put away from you, with all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; and be ye kind one to another, and tender-hearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you.</hi> This no doubt is a very fit temper for quiet, and none more unfit, then angry, waſpiſh, and domineering ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Onely this caution is to be obſerved in leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, That it be ſuch as may win men into the Church, not ſuch as may ſecure and encourage them to ſtay without. Yet lenity and gentleneſs is ſo good a Vertue, that I am loth to daſt water upon it, or ſeem to temper it.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50002:13"/>
            <p>But for men of moderate opinions, I am at a loſs to know what they ſhould be; for moderation there cannot be, but between ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams: Now what extreams are there of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions in a ſetled Church, unleſs the Church be one extream, and the Schiſmatick another? and then the man of moderate opinions is he that is part Church-man, and part Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. I hope none are ſo unkind to their Mother the Church, to charge extremities upon her Doctrine or Laws. If there be any ſuch, they are but <hi>Hybrides</hi> in Religion, and make a new ſect in the Church, as pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the peace of it as any of the reſt. The truth is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> moderate opinions are a <hi>Chimaeta,</hi> a phanſie; either nothing, or ſomewhat worſe then nothing: for poſſibly they may beſtow that good word (Moderation) upon ſuch as care little either to obſerve the Law them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or to require it of others. If theſe be the men of moderate opinions, I wonder how they will be able to give account of their juſtice and fidelity to the truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them. Yes, they ſay, very well; It is rather prudence then injuſtice, to mitigate and ſweeten the ſharpneſs and rigour of the Law. But if the Law it ſelf be too rigorous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50002:14"/>in God's name let it be amended, and not left to the arbitrary power of others to do it, for that's known to be a remedy ten times worſe then the diſeaſe. It is ſaid in Phyſick, I know not how truly, that an error in the firſt concoction, is not mended in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: It is certainly true here, an error or exceſs in the Law, which is the firſt conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of juſtice, will be ill cured afterward by an arbitrary partiality in the execution. I hope therefore no wiſe Student of quiet, will take ſuch Moderators for the beſt Miniſters of peace. But I leave them, and come to the moſt popular, and therefore moſt dangerous principle in the ſtudy of quiet; that is, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> I have ſpoken to this point heretofore in this place; yet becauſe of late our new Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Divines, as well as others, preſs hard for it, knowing without a free Market, they cannot vend their new bold ſpeculations; I ſhall reſume the point again a little more largely, yet within the compaſs of theſe two particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That there is a great deal of reaſon to <hi>reſtrain</hi> the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Secondly, That there is no reaſon to give it <hi>liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50002:14"/>
            <p n="1">1. There is reaſon enough to reſtrain the Conſcience, for the miſchief it doth to Quiet when it is at liberty; for all the diſcord and diviſions of the Church grow from hence, and that is a miſchief we have reaſon to avoid.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Mark them</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>which cauſe diviſions among you, and avoid them.</hi> There is reaſon then to mark that which cauſeth them to make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and that's the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> It is no qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etter in the Common-wealth, where it deſtroys the very Foundation of Government, and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates the Ordinance of God for it in Princes and Magiſtrates; for what is left for them to do, if every one muſt follow the dictate of his own Conſcience, that is, in plain terms, be bound onely to obey himſelf.</p>
            <p>This is no ſlander to the pretenders of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; they will ſay as much themſelves, if ye ask them. Ask the Schiſmatick why he joyns not with the congregation of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? and he will tell you, His conſcience will not ſuffer him. Ask the Rebel in the State, why he takes up Arms to the ruine of his King and Countrey? and his Conſcience will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for him, That it is Gods cauſe, and it is to do him ſervice. Ask him again, why he doth not repent of the miſchief done by it?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50002:15"/>(for that they ſeldom do) and the Conſcience will ſerve that turn too, It is Gods cauſe, and the conſcience will not ſuffer them to repent of that. Thus we ſee, the Conſcience, as it is uſed, doth not onely open a door to ſin, but ſhuts the very door to mercy, that is Repentance.</p>
            <p>If S. <hi>John</hi> ſaid true, as no doubt he did, <hi>That there were many Antichriſts,</hi> then poſſibly the <hi>Conſcience</hi> thus improved may be one of them For, it ſets it ſelf in the Church above all that is called God, yea, and God himſelf too, in a ſence; for his Laws are not to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs the <hi>Conſcience</hi> firſt allows them to be his: and thus all is reſolved into the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as the <hi>dernier</hi> reſort and laſt appeal.</p>
            <p>While the King and the Pope are contending for Supremacy, the Conſcience without ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple puts in for it againſt both, and takes it for her right to be ſupreme in all cauſes as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil. There is great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in the world of domineering over the Conſcience; but have we not rather cauſe to complain of the domineering of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? And if any liſt to ſee the Conſcience acting all this, we need go no further then our late times, when the Conſcience was loose for a while; one would think Hell had broke
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50002:15"/>looſe, ſo fill'd was on a ſudden the Church with ſects, and the Common-wealth with confuſion. There is reaſon enough therefore to reſtrain the Conſcience that acts all this, if we knew how.</p>
            <p>The next thing I undertook to ſhew, is, That there is no reaſon why it ſhould have liberty; and particularly, not that which gives the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt colour to it: Neither the duty we owe to Truth, which ſeems to have ſome right to liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; nor that we owe to the Will of God, that nothing be done againſt the Conſcience. For the firſt.</p>
            <p>Truth is that (I confeſs) which no conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of peace may warrant us to deſert; for I could never be of that opinion, That Truth in ſmaller matters may for Peace ſake be either denied or prejudiced. <hi>Magna eſt veritas etiam in minimis;</hi> in Gods name let it prevail over all. But then it muſt be <hi>Veritas in rebus,</hi> not <hi>Veritas in intellectu.</hi> For though Truth be defined to be a conformity of the underſtanding to the thing as it is indeed, yet takes the name from both; from the thing where Truth is originally, and from the underſtanding where it is onely repreſented. Truth in that firſt reference to the thing, admits no qualification; things
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50002:16"/>muſt be taken as they are, be they never ſo ſmall: but as the things come to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, and entertained by the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by reaſon of the miſtakes and errours that may happen in that, though Truth it ſelf, or Truth in the thing cannot, yet my apprehenſion of it may both yield to better, and may ſometimes be waved for peace ſake. To argue from Truth in the thing, to Truth in the appehenſion onely, is a fallacy againſt the Rules of Reaſoning, we call it <hi>Petitio prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii,</hi> or a begging of the queſtion. If a Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhould beg an alms, I wiſh he may have it; but he ſhall beg long ere it be granted him, that he hath the truth. How then can he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon that truth, to which he hath no other title but his own perſwaſion, which can be no better then any mans elſe, who is as ſtrongly perſwaded to the contrary? And this is all the ſervice that Truth can do the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for liberty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing whereupon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience eſpecially bears it ſelf ſo high, is the Will of God that nothing be done againſt the Conſcience. That no doubt is a great offence, and made ſo by the greateſt Authority: Yet the ſame God that requires our obedience to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50002:16"/>the Conſcience, commands us likewiſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey our Parents, our Princes and Governours, and all theſe ſtand upon as good authority as the Conſcience. If we cannot reconcile our obedience to that with our obedience to theſe, we may ſin againſt God, when we do not ſin againſt the Conſcience. For though God hath erected a Tribunal in every mans breaſt, and there ſet the Conſcience to be a Judge of all our actions, there be other Tribunals of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice beſides, of Gods erection too, and to which he hath ſubjected the very Conſcience. <hi>Ye muſt needs be ſubject</hi> (Rom. 13.) <hi>not onely for wrath, but alſo for conſcience.</hi> And after both theſe, there is another Tribunal in Heaven, to which all Judges, Conſcience and all muſt give an account one day. For the Conſcience is no Court of Record; the Decrees and Acts paſſed there, will be no good evidence at that Bar; there all muſt be re-examined, and tried over again. <hi>Though I know nothing by my ſelf,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>yet am I not thereby juſtified.</hi> Though he could not charge his Conſcience with any offence, he knew a further trial muſt paſs upon him before he could be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved. My Conſcience indeed may be pleaded there in evidence againſt me as a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50002:17"/>to condemn me, but not as a Judge to abſolve me. It is a great miſtake in the power and operation of the Conſcience: That it will condemn us, if we do any thing againſt it, the Text is clear for that; but that it will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve us for that we do according to it, there is no Text, I am ſure, for that We muſt then be tried by the Law, and not by the Conſcience: For how the proceedings will be at that Bar, we have a record, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31. <hi>When the Son of Man ſhall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him; Then ſhall be ſit upon the throne of his glory, and before him ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered all nations.</hi> When the Court was ſet, the Charge was given to thoſe on the left hand; <hi>I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat; I was athirſt, and ye gave me no drink; I was a ſtranger, and ye took me not in; naked, and ye cloathed me not; ſick and in priſon, and ye viſited me not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Charge the Conſcience (no doubt confidently enough) pleaded <hi>Not guilty; Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, or athirſt, or a ſtranger, or naked, or ſick, or in priſon, and did not miniſter unto thee?</hi> Their Conſcience could accuſe them of none of theſe things; for all that, the Sentence went againſt them upon a point of Law and Equity; <hi>In that ye did it not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50002:17"/>to theſe</hi> (ſaith the Judge) <hi>ye did it not to me.</hi> And for this they were condemned to eternal puniſhment.</p>
            <p>If they that ſtand ſo much upon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences did ſeriouſly conſider this, they would find as little cauſe to deſire that liberty, as there is to grant it, ſeeing it ſtands them in ſo little ſtead when they have moſt need of it; for when they think their conſcience ſhall anſwer for them, they muſt then anſwer for their conſcience, and upon trial, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may prove the great offender. Thus have I hitherto given you an account of ſome of the vulgar miſtaken principles of Quiet, which our Student is firſt to unlearn; which are all but the patching up of a falſe deceitful peace, condemned in the Politicks under the name of a <hi>Syncretiſmus,</hi> when all the Factions in <hi>Crete</hi> joyn'd together in a common danger, which laſted no longer then the cauſe of it: like the bonds of a hard. Froſt, that binds Earth and Water, Sticks and Stones all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, till the Sun comes to ſhine upon them, and then they all preſently return to their proper place and nature again.</p>
            <p>But I fear I have run out all my time almoſt in theſe miſtaken ways of peace: I preſume
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50002:18"/>it will be a greater offence to leave you here now, then to beg a little more time to ſet you in the right way, though I ſhall not go beyond the office of a <hi>Mercury,</hi> to point the hand where it lies.</p>
            <p>There is the Kings high-way to peace, and the Students private way, and both good in their kind. With the Kings way I ſhall not meddle, as being fitter matter for our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs then inſtruction, who hath already paved the way for us by wholſom Laws for that purpoſe. But becauſe oft times <hi>Vitia ſunt remediis fortiora,</hi> the compulſory way by Law, though always neceſſary, is not always ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; to the Kings way we muſt add the Students alſo: That every one in his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular makes it his care and buſineſs to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to it, that it be an artificial ſtudied peace, to which not Fear onely, but Conſcience of Duty and Religion obligeth us.</p>
            <p>Now every good Student of any Science ſearches into the true and proper cauſe of things; for, <hi>Scire eſt per cauſas cognoſcere.</hi> If the cauſe of all diviſion in the Church, be differing in judgment, nothing can cure that but a conſent. S. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore preſcribes that for the remedy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>That there
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50002:18"/>be no diviſions among you;</hi> how may that be helped? it follows, <hi>But that ye be perfectly joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> This is the true Apoſtolical Principle, whereon we are to ground our Study of Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et: For all the fine things and ſentences that are ſpoken for peace and quiet, will little move thoſe that are, and may very well be confident, they ought not howſoever have peace with Sin, or Error. Unleſs therefore we can be firſt perſwaded that we ought not to charge the Church with either, we do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for Peace. This I confeſs is the great difficulty, yet if this be not done, there can be no hope of Peace.</p>
            <p>And to do this, I ſhall not ſend our Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Polemick School, to convince him out of ſpeculative Principles of Reaſon and Divinity; for to that ſtudy, ſome have not capacity, others not leiſure: I ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend to him ſome practical Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, obvious to all, and denied by none, that out of them he may learn not to diſſent from, or condemn the Church of Errour.</p>
            <p>To prevent the paſſing that ſentence, let the Student
<list>
                  <item>1. Study himſelf, his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</item>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:50002:19"/>
                  <item>2. Let him ſtudy the Church againſt which he paſſeth ſentence.</item>
                  <item>3. Let him ſtudy the nature and quality of the things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon judgement is given.</item>
                  <item>4. Let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well the manner of proceeding in judgement.</item>
               </list> In all which we ſhall find ſome known Principle of Religion to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, In the ſtudy of our ſelves, and our own condition: Religion teacheth us to have an humble, lowly, mean opinion of our ſelves; and not without cauſe, whether we reſpect our Underſtandings, or our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: Our Underſtandings are naturally weak, imperfect, ſhort-ſighted, we know but in part, the beſt of us; and our Affections too are diſloyal to our Underſtandings, <hi>The heart of man,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>is deceitfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things.</hi> We have little reaſon then to truſt our ſelves much in either. He that is truly conſcious of his own weakneſs or lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will be content to be ſupported by others. If we ſtudy this point well, our own infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we ſhould learn more willingly to aſſent to, and take ſupport from the Church.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, if in the ſecond place, we ſtudy that too whoſe Governors Religion likewiſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50002:19"/>teaches us to obey, <hi>For they watch over our ſouls,</hi> Heb. 13.17. If it be a good point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>in lowlineſs of mind to eſteem others better then our ſelves,</hi> Phil. 2.3. it is Religion and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon both, to think our Governors wiſer too; for there is a preſumption always in favour of them. S. <hi>Paul</hi> gives it for a rule to <hi>Timothy, Not to receive an accuſation againſt an Elder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>but before two or three witneſſes,</hi> becauſe it is to be preſum'd on the part of Age and Authority, to know more, and offend leſs. But when it comes to be the whole Elderſhip, all our Governors joyntly, the preſumption is ſo much the ſtronger. If we add this ſtudy to the former, how little reaſon we have to truſt our ſelves, and how much we have to truſt our Governors, we will not raſhly paſs ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt them, if we have either Reaſon or Religion in us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And yet we have more work for our Student; Let him, in the third place, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the nature and quality of the things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon judgement is given, how apt they are to deceive us. Truth is many times ſo like an Errour, and Errour comes ſo near to Truth, that he had need be carefull and circumſpect that ſhall diſtinguiſh them in ſome caſes. And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50002:20"/>in others again, Truth lies hid under many folds, eſpecially ambiguity of words, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cheat of all Students, who are more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deceiv'd into opinions then convinc'd. It is not ſtrange to ſee ſo many go aſtray from the Church, to whom the things of it are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented under the covert of falſe names, when they hear the Government of it called Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; obedience, ſlavery; contempt, courage; licence, liberty; frenzy, zeal; order, ſuperſtition. How eaſily thus may ſimple people miſtake their way, and fall into the pit that's cover'd over with ſhadows and falſe names of things? When he hath ſtudied this point well,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let him, in the fourth place, be well adviſed in what manner he proceeds in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and upon what evidence: For, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conſcience to be a Judge, it muſt not treſpaſs upon the Rules of good Judicature, as, both ſides muſt be heard impartially, which is ſeldom done; the <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt not be miſ-led no more then other Judges, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, paſſion, or favour; for what can that judgment be worth which is perverted by any of theſe. Now if we examine how moſt men come to paſs ſentence againſt the Church, we ſhall finde it to be upon very ſlight evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50002:20"/>It may be their Education, they have been always brought up that way; for Sects commonly run in a blood, in a family: Or they have been ſo taught, they ſay, by good men; that indeed is the ſum and upſhot of the Faith of moſt that diſſent, the credit given to ſome weak, private, ignorant Inſtructer, whoſe perſon they have in admitation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great cauſe, God knows; whereas their private judgments, becauſe they are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ought always to be ſupected, if we be wiſe; and becauſe againſt their Governours, to be contemn'd, if we be obedient.</p>
            <p>All theſe well ſtudied, may make for peace, when poſſibly Arguments, and Diſputes, and Puniſhments too will not do it. And yet if ſtill none of theſe will make our Student quiet,</p>
            <p>Let him, in the laſt place, make trial of a common remedy that prevails in all caſes of difficulty: Let him but ſtudy his own ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the ſafeſt courſe, and he ſhall finde that better provided for in the Churches judgment, then in his own; for, if he ſhould erre in following the Church, or his Governors, for that is poſſible, the greateſt part of that guilt, ſome ſay all, I ſay onely the greateſt part,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50002:21"/>muſt lie at their door that command that which is unlawfull: But if they ſhould erre in following their own judgment, or a Judge of their own chooſing, for that makes it their own too, and that is more then poſſible, all the blame and guilt then muſt of neceſsity and inexcuſably fall upon themſelves. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe principles, ſetting aſide all thoſe that may convince our judgments in particulars, from theſe alone, I ſay, we ſee how ſafe, how prudent, how religious a thing it is to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our private judgments to the publick, for the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>It remains onely now, that we imploy our beſt endeavour and ſtudy for it, which is the ſecond part of the Text, and the laſt thing to be conſidered,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ye ſtudy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>STudy is an earneſt intention of the mind, by diligent ſearch and enquiry. Wiſhing well to Quiet, or ſpeaking well of it, will not ſerve; the greateſt diſturbers of Peace will do that many times, give it a good word, when they will not part with a phanſie for it. And yet Quiet is a thing that requires care and pains ſomewhat more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: For when S. <hi>Peter</hi> likewiſe ſpeaks of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50002:21"/>peace, it is in words of the ſame import, <hi>Seek peace, and enſue it.</hi> If it be hidden,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.11</note> ſeek it out; if it flies from you, purſue after it. It is a buſie thing to be quiet. The word here tranſlated, <hi>Study,</hi> is in the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Be ambitious of it;</hi> that is, purſue and ſtudy it as you would do Honour and Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And that, I think, is as much as can be deſired; and yet no more then Quiet both deſerves and needs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It deſerves it. For though quiet be rather <hi>Status vitae,</hi> then <hi>Virtus;</hi> it is no Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it ſelf, yet the beſt ſoil to plant Vertue in <hi>The fruits of righteouſneſs are ſown in peace,</hi> Jam. 3.18. So are all the fruits of Induſtry; Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Arts, Sciences, Traffick, Commerce, flouriſh moſt in the calm temperate clime; but in troubles and diſſentions every good thing goes backward, onely miſchief thrives It fares with troubled times, as in troubled waters; all the filth, dirt and mire in the bottom gets then up to the top. We ſaw as much when our waters were lately troubled; what a deal of filth, dirt and mire, what ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did ſtuff was then got up to the top and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place of rule and command? So much are we the more oblig'd to ſtudy that peace
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50002:22"/>and quiet, which hath ſunk them to their proper place again, the bottom: And there let them lie, if you would be quiet.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it deſerves therefore our ſtudy, ſo it needs it too; for it is a difficult thing to be quiet, the way to it lies through ſo many parts and duties of Religion, and not the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt of them neither: To deny our ſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> humility and lowlineſs of mind to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our own weakneſs and frailty, to ſubmit our judgments to others, as better and wiſer then our ſelves; to ſubdue our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and luſts, from whence the Apoſtle ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves <hi>Wars and Contentions</hi> to come, <hi>from our Luſts;</hi> and to all theſe the Fleſh hath natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a reluctance. Our Student therefore hath need to contend with himſelf to be at peace with others.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> was at <hi>Athens</hi> when he wrote this Epiſtle, a famous Univerſity for the ſtudy of all liberal Arts and Sciences. I cannot ſay he had theſe in his thought, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended this ſtudy to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> as an Art of more uſe then any he found at <hi>Athens:</hi> Yet when I ſee him ſo paſsionately earneſt for it, to beſeech them to ſtudy, we have reaſon to value it as an Art well worthy of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50002:22"/>Schools, and Profeſſors, and Students. And they would make <hi>a Royal Society,</hi> whereof the King himſelf is Maſter, who is our Peace-maker by office, and by a care equal to that, hath by Law provided,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> that <hi>under Him we may live a peaceable and quiet life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> He hath little ſenſe of Honour, that will not enter himſelf a Student under that conduct. The very word for <hi>Study,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, carries Honour in it.</p>
            <p>And yet I can tell them of a higher School for it then this, and wherein Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are content to be Students. Our Lord Chriſt, the great Mediator of our eternal peace with Heaven, would not be brought into the world without a Song of Peace on Earth, by Angels: And when he left the World, bequeathed it as a Legacy after him, <hi>My peace I leave with you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Joh. 14.27.</note> And when he comes again to judge the world, we have reaſon to look that he will call us to a reckoning how we uſe his Legacy. And ſo he will too; for he is that Lord, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. that when he came and found ſome ſmiting their fellow-ſervants, commanded them to be cut aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and have their portion with hypocrites: A puniſhment well fitted to the offence;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50002:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>there was a ſchiſme in the fault, and there ſhall be another ſchiſme in the puniſhment; they who ſundred and divided from their Brethren, ſhould themſelves be cut aſunder, and have their portion with hypocrites. But for the Peace-makers, when he comes, he will provide better company, for <hi>they ſhall be called the Children of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.9.</note> Bleſſed are they then whom the Lord when he comes ſhall finde at their ſtudies of that Quiet which gives them ſo fair a Title to Eternal Reſt and Peace in Heaven with Chriſt, and all the Children of God.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
